Guide to the Eric Alfred Havelock Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings, Research, and Teaching Files, 1930-1988; Series V
  - History of Early Greek Mind [vols. II, III, notes], Undated (Box 47)
  - PrePlatonics: miscellanea, 1972, 1979 (Box 47)
  - Notes [chapter 19], Undated (Box 47)
  - Psyche, Dialectic, Undated (Box 47)
  - The Struggle to Think-Wits and Senses/Separation of Intellect [chapter 22], Undated (Box 47)
  - Origins materials discarded, Undated (Box 48)
  - Liberal creed?, Undated (Box 48)
  - Social political essays, 1945 (Box 48)
  - Political Sophists/P&A Stoics, Undated (Box 48)
  - Greek Mind, Undated (Box 48)
  - Protomorality [notes], Undated (Box 48)
  - Conscious Ethic, Undated (Box 48)
  - Cardinal Habits, Protomorality, Wits and Senses, Dawn of Abstract Intellect, Undated (Box 48)
  - The Greek Experience [carbons I (Iliad), carbon II, (Odyssey)], 1966, 1967 (Box 48)
  - CC10a, Plato's Republic, Undated (Box 48)
  - CC10, Iliad, 1965 (Box 48)
  - CC10, Herodotus, 1966 (Box 48)
  - CC10 [I-IV, miscellaneous], 1963-1966 (Box 49)
  - Ethics of Negotiation [Social Sciences 117]
    - Vols. I, II [handwritten drafts, bibliography, clippings], 1957-1960 (Box 50)
    - Cuba, Undated (Box 50)
    - World politics, news events, clippings [nine folders], 1960-1968 (Box 50)
    - Cuban missile crisis [two volumes of clippings], Undated (Box 51)
  - Essays on Greek intellectual history [reprints/articles written or works edited by Havelock, unsorted material], Undated (Box 52)
  - Bibliography abstracts circa 1656-1938 (Box 53)
  - T Be in Agam/Dik-in Oresteia statistics, Undated (Box 53)
  - Greek compositions, Undated (Box 53)
  - The Oral Education of Athens: Some Anecdotal Evidences in Plutarch, Undated (Box 53)
  - Bibliography, general, Undated (Box 53)
  - Hippolytus, Undated (Box 53)
  - Ethics of Negotiation files, notes, clippings [folder numbers may relate to chapter numbers], Undated (Box 54)
  - Pomeroy, Sarah, 1984-1986 (Box 54)
  - Raffel, Burton, 1986 (Box 54)
  - Union of Concerned Scientists/SANE Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy, 1985, 1986 (Box 54)
  - New Orleans Conference on College Composition and Communication, 1986 March (Box 54)
  - Goold, George, 1985, 1986 (Box 54)
  - Kilpatrick, Ross, 1985, 1986 (Box 54)
  - Georgopoulos, N., 1986 (Box 54)
  - Gagarin, Michael, 1975-1985 (Box 54)
  - Beil Waugh, Joanne, 1984-1986 (Box 54)
  - Blanchard, Lydia, 1986-1987 (Box 54)
  - Comune di Firenze, 1982 (Box 54)
  - Alphabetic mind [six folders of notes], Undated (Box 54)
  - Muse, Undated (Box 54)
  - Special Theory of Greek Orality, 700-600 B.C., Undated (Box 54)
  - Ethics of Negotiation [clippings, notes, drafts], 1982-1985,undated (Box 55)
  - Unpublished papers
    - A Textualized Invention, Undated (Box 55)
    - The Alphabet as the Creator of Modern Culture, Undated (Box 55)
    - Oral Elements in the Composition of the Oedipus Tyrannus, Undated (Box 55)
    - Hippolytus, Undated (Box 55)
  - Book lists, 1957-1968 (Box 55)
  - Literary evidence notes [chapter 8], Undated (Box 55)
  - Moral Structure of the Odyssey/Metrical Tables of Athonisms [chapter 10], Undated (Box 55)
  - Syntax of Oral Proposition, Undated (Box 55)
  - Alphabetization notes, Undated (Box 55)
  - Literary bibliography, Bloomfield and Dunn, Undated (Box 55)
  - Aftermath of Alphabet, Undated (Box 56)
  - Shapes of Literacy, Undated (Box 56)
  - Alphabetization, Undated (Box 56)
  - The Five Greek Syllabaries, Undated (Box 56)
  - Documentation of Discourse, Undated (Box 56)
  - Moral Structure of the Iliad, Undated (Box 56)
  - Justice of Solon [residual notes], Undated (Box 56)
  - Literacy, Undated (Box 56)
  - Sound and Sign?, Undated (Box 56)
  - Memorization/Concept, Undated (Box 56)
  - Literary transcript discarded, Undated (Box 56)
  - Birth, Undated (Box 56)
  - Literacy: items on language and culture, Undated (Box 56)
  - Notes on Concept and Literacy, Undated (Box 56)
  - Negotiation/Suez/Korean plane, 1985, undated (Box 56)
  - Clouds, Undated (Box 56)
  - Orality, Literacy, and Star Wars, Undated (Box 56)
  - Muse, Undated (Box 56)
  - Literacy and Law, Undated (Box 56)
  - Alpahabetic Mind: Greek Lyric, Undated (Box 56)
  - Special Theory of Greek Orality, Undated (Box 56)
  - The Oral-Literate Equation: A Formula for the Modern Mind [paper presented at Oral and Literacy Conference, Toronto], 1987 (Box 57)
  - Page, Denys Lionel, [1962?] (Box 57)
  - Robb, Kevin [correspondence, proposed guide to Plato's Republic], 1974-1986 (Box 57)
  - Swearingen, C. Jan [correspondence], 1982-1988 (Box 57)
  - Smith College, 1987, undated (Box 57)
  - Causes, political, 1967, undated (Box 57)
  - Brandeis University, 1965 (Box 57)
  - Greek drama bibliography, Undated (Box 57)
  - Aeneid, Undated (Box 57)
  - Alphabet and Islam, Undated (Box 57)
  - Catullus, Undated (Box 57)
  - Coming of Literate Communication to Western Culture, Undated (Box 57)
  - Classics 371, Greek theater, Undated (Box 57)
  - Drama, Undated (Box 57)
  - Song of Iopas, 1972 (Box 57)
  - Geometric Greece, Undated (Box 57)
  - Heracles, Undated (Box 57)
  - Greek art/literature, Undated (Box 57)
  - Hesiod, 1982 (Box 57)
  - Melos, 1981 (Box 57)
  - Plato's Invention, Undated (Box 57)
  - Professional Technique of Sophists, Undated (Box 57)
  - Virgil, Undated (Box 57)
  - Oedipus [discards?], Undated (Box 58)
  - Radcliffe trusteeship, 1959-1963 (Box 58)
  - Innis, Harold, Undated (Box 58)
  - Papers to be read [with accompanying correspondence], 1968-1972, undated (Box 58)
  - Greek Muse Learns to Write [vol. II typescript drafts], Undated (Box 58)
  - Muse [extra materials], Undated (Box 58)
  - History of the Greek Mind [vol. II typescript], Undated (Box 58)
  - Concerning Homer, Date and Composition [notes], Undated (Box 58)
  - Methuen, Undated (Box 58)
  - Orality of Socrates and Literacy of Plato, Undated (Box 58)
  - Homer [notes, miscellany], Undated (Box 58)
  - Socrates, articles on, 1934, 1952, 1969, 1972, 1983-1986 (Box 59)
  - Man of Athens: Socrates [incomplete manuscript/notes], Undated (Box 59)
  - The Hippolytus of Euripides: An English Translation, by EAH [an acting version], 1984 (Box 59)
  - Clippings [language, literature, education], 1960s-1970s (Box 59)
- Yale Classics Department Files, 1932-1971; Series VI
  This series consists of files compiled by Havelock during his time at Yale as chairman of the Classics Department. They are arranged in two sections, correspondence and topical files, and alphabetically within each section. There is overlap between the two sections. The papers contain correspondence of Havelock either with or about individuals, most of whom served in the Classics Department in some capacity; requests for recommendations and copies thereof; requests to participate in seminars/conferences; official records of appointments, leaves of absence, and finances; and letters and memos to university administrators. The materials reflect the challenges of reorganization of the department dealt with by Havelock as chairman.
  - Correspondence
    - Pre-arrival at Yale, 1962-1963 (Box 60, Folder 1)
    - Congratulatory messages re appointment, 1963 (Box 60, Folder 2)
    - Astin, Alan E. [includes correspondence with history department], 1966-1967 (Box 60, Folder 3-6)
    - Bowersock, Glen [Welles file], 1963, 1965 (Box 60, Folder 7)
    - Brewster, Kingman, Jr., 1963-1965 (Box 60, Folder 8)
    - Buttrey, Theodore V., 1954-1966 (Box 60, Folder 9)
    - Clausen, Wendell, 1964-1967, undated (Box 60, Folder 10)
    - Commager, Steele, 1964-1965, 1968 (Box 60, Folder 11)
    - Coulter, James A., 1966 (Box 60, Folder 12)
    - Curran, Leo C., 1957-1966, undated (Box 60, Folder 13)
    - Doeblin, Richard [and Shechter], 1964-1967, undated (Box 60, Folder 14-15)
    - Goar, Robert, 1966 (Box 60, Folder 16)
    - Goold, George, 1964 (Box 60, Folder 17)
    - Gould, Thomas, 1971 (Box 60, Folder 18)
    - Hall, Alan S., 1968 (Box 60, Folder 19)
    - Kirk, Geoffrey S., 1963-1967 (Box 60, Folder 20-21)
    - Knauer, Georg, 1966-1967 (Box 60, Folder 22)
    - Lloyd-Jones, Hugh, 1965-1967 (Box 60, Folder 23)
    - McLuhan, Marshall, 1968 (Box 60, Folder 24)
    - Munari, Franco, 1965 (Box 60, Folder 25)
    - O'Brien, Michael John, 1956-1965, undated (Box 60, Folder 26-28)
    - Parry, Adam M., 1959-1968, undated (Box 60, Folder 29-32)
    - Perkins, Ann, 1949-1964, undated (Box 61, Folder 33-34)
    - Richardson, Emeline Hill, 1963-1965 (Box 61, Folder 35)
    - Richardson, Lawrence, 1955-1960, 1962-1966 (Box 61, Folder 36)
    - Robb, Kevin, 1965-1968 (Box 61, Folder 37)
    - Samuel, Alan, 1932, 1953-1967 (Box 61, Folder 38-40)
    - Scholars, correspondence with, 1961, 1965-1968 (Box 61, Folder 41-44)
    - Segal, Erich, 1967-1968 (Box 61, Folder 45)
    - Shechter, Stanley, 1963, 1966 (Box 61, Folder 46)
    - Silk, Edmund, 1965-1966 (Box 61, Folder 47)
    - Welles, C. Bradford [includes file on Ann Perkins], 1934, 1938-1939, 1946, 1950-1951, 1962-1966 (Box 61, Folder 48-54)
  - Topical files [with accompanying correspondence]
    Conditions Governing Access
    Folders 55-57 in Series VI are restricted until January 1, 2040.
    - Appointment ["Yale's promises"], 1963 (Box 62, Folder 55)
    - Appointments of others [includes finances], 1959-1964 (Box 62, Folder 56-57)
    - Budget, 1950-1964 (Box 62, Folder 58-60)
    - Classics Library, 1964-1966 (Box 62, Folder 61)
    - Departmental crises/decisions, miscellaneous, 1965-1968, undated (Box 62, Folder 62)
    - Departmental policies, 1964-1966 (Box 62, Folder 63)
    - Enrollment statistics, 1966-1968 (Box 62, Folder 64)
    - Graduate studies [general, procedures, includes degree lists from 1947-1965], 1947-1968 (Box 62, Folder 65-67)
    - Minutes of department meetings, 1965-1968 (Box 62, Folder 68-71)
    - "Miscellaneous papers from Phelps Hall", 1961-1968, undated (Box 62, Folder 72-74)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities Fellowship, 1967, 1968 (Box 62, Folder 75)
    - Notebooks [kept by EAH during his chairmanship], 1966-1970s (Box 63, Folder 76-78)
    - Philosophy-Classics degree, 1967 (Box 63, Folder 79)
    - Philosophy Department, 1964, undated (Box 63, Folder 80)
    - Publicity [press releases, clippings], 1965 (Box 63, Folder 81)
    - San Francisco [departmental party], 1969-1970 (Box 63, Folder 82)
    - Staffing [charts], 1962-1965 (Box 63, Folder 83)
    - Sterling research grant funding, 1967 (Box 63, Folder 84)
    - Yale Daily News [re controversy in department], 1966 (Box 63, Folder 85)
    - Yale/Vassar Study, 1967 (Box 63, Folder 86-87)
- Oversize, 1921-1945
  - Co-operative Commonwealth Federation (CCF)
    - Annual conventions, 1944-1945, undated (Box 64)
    - Campaign poster of EAH, 1945 (Box 64)
    - [partial newspaper], 1945 (Box 64)
    - Constituency files
      - General provincial [chart], 1944 (Box 64)
      - Ontario, Undated (Box 64)
      - Spadina, 1942, 1944, undated (Box 64)
      - Wellington South and North, 1933, 1945 (Box 64)
    - Labor/Progressive Party [articles], 1945 (Box 64)
    - Legislative Assembly, Toronto [floor plan, second session, twenty-first legislature], 1945 February (Box 64)
    - Lists of Parliament members, union leaders, CCF leaders and candidates, 1943-1945 (Box 64)
  - Personal papers [Oxford and Cambridge Schools Examination Board certificates; University of Cambridge, B.A., M.A.], 1921, 1922, 1926, 1929 (Box 64)